# Joao Garcia

https://www.joaomgarcia.com https://jmbvgarcia.github.io/ joao\_garcia@brown.edu

### **BROWN UNIVERSITY**

Placement Director: Toru Kitagawa toru\_kitagawa@brown.edu 401-863-3688 Graduate Administrator: Angelica Spertini angelica\_spertini@brown.edu 401-863-2465

#### Office Contact Information

Department of Economics, Box B Brown University Providence, Rhode Island 02912 phone: +1 (202) 9078734

#### References

Professor Andrew Foster
Department of Economics, Box B
Brown University
Providence, Rhode Island 02912
afoster@brown.edu

Professor Bryce Steinberg
Department of Economics, Box B
Brown University
Providence, Rhode Island 02912
bryce\_steinberg@brown.edu

Professor **Neil Thakral**Department of Economics, Box B
Brown University
Providence, Rhode Island 02912
neil thakral@brown.edu

# Job Market Paper

## Free Childcare and the Motherhood Penalty: Evidence from São Paulo

with Marcela Mello and Rafael Latham-Proenca

Latin America consistently has some of the world's largest child penalties (or motherhood penalties) for women, and while subsidized childcare is often advanced as a remedy, the literature on its effectiveness is scarce outside developed countries. This paper estimates the impact of a rapid expansion of public childcare on mothers' careers in the city of São Paulo. We leverage the precise location and timing of the expansion of childcare facilities, coupled with detailed data on the labor market and household characteristics to identify effects on mothers' labor market participation and earnings. Using a difference-in-differences approach, we compare the child penalty in districts that experienced a large and rapid expansion of childcare with districts with no significant expansion. Our results show that an additional seat per child leads to an increase of 6.4 p.p. (20%) in the mothers' formal employment after the first child's birth. We do not detect any effect of this expansion on two comparison groups: mothers-to-be and fathers.

# Working Papers

Optimizing Incentives for Solar: Accounting for Regional Differences in Emissions

Child Disability and Mothers' Work: Evidence from the Zika Virus Outbreak With Marcela Mello and Rafael Latham-Proença

### Teaching

- Brown Graduate: Macroeconomics, Econometrics
- Brown MPA: Microeconomics, Statistics, Econometrics, Public Policy
- Brown Undergraduate: Environmental Economics, Public Economics, Health Economics

## **EDUCATION**

Brown University Providence, RI, USA
Ph.D. Candidate in Economics 2018 –May 2024 (Expected)

**Fundacao Getulio Vargas**M.A. Economics
Sao Paulo, Brazil
2015 –2015

University of Sao Paulo, Brazil
B.A. Economics
Sao Paulo, Brazil
2009 –2013

## WORK EXPERIENCE

- Research Assistant: Professor David Weil (2018–2019)
- Pre-Doctoral Research Assistant: Professors Dave Donaldson, Dina Pomeranz, Monica Singhal and Paul Carrillo (2016–2017)
- Summer Internship: Wayfair Inc. (2022)

#### OTHER.

- Nationality: Brazilian
- Languages: Fluent English, Native Portuguese, Advanced Spanish
- Conferences: NEUDC 2022; Monash Environmental Economics Workshop 2023